Catholic Church, Diocese of Tucson Records, 1721-1957
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Records of the Catholic Church, Diocese of Tucson, 1721-1957
MS 296
Catholic Church. -- Diocese of Tucson (Ariz.)
The bulk of the records in this collection are holographic sacramental registers that document baptisms, marriages, burials and confirmations of individual church members from 1863 until 1903, from parish and mission churches under the supervision of the Vicariate Apostolic of New Mexico (1850-1867), the Vicariate Apostolic of Arizona (1868-1896) and the Diocese of Tucson (1897-present). Two earlier registers from the Spanish Colonial Period document baptisms, marriages and burials from the missions of Tubac and Calabasas-Tumacacori under the administrative supervision of the Diocese of Durango (1620-1778) and the Diocese of Sonora (1779-1829).
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are some restrictions on the use of this collection. Users of this collection may photocopy only those entries specific to their research. The registers may not be copied in their entirety. Permission must be obtained from the Diocese of Tucson
Historical Note
As New Spain expanded northward from the Valley of Mexico, new dioceses of the Catholic Church were established to administer the spiritual conquests of the missionary padres; the Diocese of Guadalajara in 1548, the Diocese of Durango in 1620. As the frontier became consolidated, the old dioceses were subdivided. In 1779, southern Arizona and parts of southern New Mexico became part of the newly created Diocese of Sonora, under Bishop Antonio Reyes, who had been one of the earliest Franciscan missionaries in Pimería Alta.
Following the Mexican War of 1848 and the Gadsden Purchase of 1854, new ecclesiastical administration problems arose. A large number of Mexican and Native Americans had been added to the Catholic population of the United States. At the request of American Bishops, Pope Pius IX created the Vicariate Apostolic of New Mexico on July 19, 1850 and appointed Fr. John B. Lamy, as Vicar Apostolic with the title of Bishop of Agathonica.
In January of 1866, Bishop Lamy sent Fathers John B. Salpointe, Francis Boucard, Patrick Birmingham and a seminarian, Mr. Vincent from Santa Fe to Tucson. Father Birmingham became the first pastor of Gila City, near present day Yuma. Fathers Salpointe and Boucard established the parish of Saint Augustine in Tucson with San Xavier del Bac as their largest mission. Mr. Vincent opened a school at San Xavier and later in Tucson. Two years later, the Vicariate Apostolic of Arizona was formed with Father Salpointe as Vicar Apostolic. His Vicariate extended from Utah to Mexico, from El Paso County in Texas to Yuma. In 1897, the Diocese of Tucson was formed.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Diocese of Durange and Diocese of Sonora, 1721-1826
Series II: Vicariate Apostolic of New Mexico, the Vicariate Apostolic of Arizona and the Diocese of Tucson, 1863-1957
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the records in this collection are holographic sacramental registers that document baptisms, marriages, burials and confirmations of individual church members from 1863 until 1903, from parish and mission churches under the supervision of the Vicariate Apostolic of New Mexico (1850-1867), the Vicariate Apostolic of Arizona (1868-1896) and the Diocese of Tucson (1897-present). Two earlier registers from the Spanish Colonial Period document baptisms, marriages and burials from the missions of Tubac and Calabasas-Tumacacori under the administrative supervision of the Diocese of Durango (1620-1778) and the Diocese of Sonora (1779-1829). The records of the local chapters of the Rosary Society and the Society for the Propagation of the Faith associated with the Cathedral of Saint Augustine are included in Volume 11 along with a six page reminiscence written by Petra Figueroa Stevenson, a member of the Saint Augustine congregation.
The records from Yuma (Volume 12) include the communities of Ehrenberg, La Paz and Prescott. The records from Solomonville (Volume 13) represent a large number of small communities in New Mexico - Buena Vista, El Paso, Lordsburgh and Virden and Arizona -Arivaipa, Bisbee, Bonita, Bowie, Camp Grant, Carlisle, Clifton, Dos Cabezas, Duncan, Fort Apache, Fort Thomas, Geronimo, Globe, Klondike, Lost Gulch, Metcalf, Morenci, Paredis, Pearce, Pima, Safford, San Antonio of the Gila, San Carlos, San Pedro, Stein Pass, Thatcher, Willcox, and Yachina.
Volume 24 consists of a holographic three page "History of the Catholic Church of Tombstone" written by Bishop Salpointe ca. 1881. Volume 25 contains several miscellaneous lists including: the names of parishes and pastors in the state of Sonora, Mexico, the names of priests found in the baptismal registers of the Cathedral of Saint Augustine in Tucson and an index to baptismal registers of Silverbell and Sasco, 1903-1913.
Cathedral of San Augustine (Tucson, Ariz.) -- History; Catholic Church. -- Diocese of Durango (Mexico) -- Registers; Catholic Church. -- Diocese of Sonora (Mexico) -- Registers; Catholic Church. -- Diocese of Tucson (Ariz.) -- Registers; Church of the Assumption (Florence, Ariz.) -- History; Church of the Immaculate Conception (Yuma, Ariz.) -- History; Church of Our Blessed Lady of Lourdes (Benson, Ariz.) -- History; Catholic Church -- Arizona -- History; Catholic Church -- New Mexico -- History; Catholic Church -- Mexico -- Sonora (State) -- History; Church records and registers -- Arizona; Church records and registers -- New Mexico; Church buildings -- Arizona -- Calabasas; Church buildings -- Arizona -- Solomonville; Church buildings -- Arizona -- Tubac; Church buildings -- Arizona -- Tombstone; Church buildings -- Arizona -- Tumacacori; Registers; Annals; Baptismal Records
Container List
- Series I: Diocese of Durange and Diocese of Sonora, 1721-1826
  - Tubaca
    - Baptismal Register. 1721-1763 (Volume 1)
  - Calabasas and Tumacacori
    - Baptismal Register. 1769-1826 (Volume 2)
- Series II: Vicariate Apostolic of New Mexico, the Vicariate Apostolic of Arizona and the Diocese of Tucson, 1863-1957
  - Tucson -- Cathedral of Saint Augustine
    - Baptismal Register. 1863-1878 (Volume 3)
    - Baptismal Register. 1879-1882 (Volume 4)
    - Baptismal Register. 1883-1885 (Volume 5)
    - Baptismal Register. 1885-1888 (Volume 6)
    - Baptismal Register. 1888-1891 (Volume 7)
    - Baptismal Register. 1891-1893 (Volume 8)
    - Baptismal Register. 1893-1896 (Volume 9)
    - Baptismal Register. 1896-1903 (Volume 10)
    - Records of the Rosary Society. 1866-1867, 1872, 1877, 1882, 1885, 1893, 1896-1897 & 1899 (Volume 11)
    - Burials of the Holy Hope Cemetery. 1948-1952 (Volume 11)
    - Society for the Propagation of the Faith. 1867 (Volume 11)
    - Confirmations. 1875-1876 (Volume 11)
    - "Persons mentioned in this book that I used to know" Historical reminiscences by Petra Figueroa Stevenson Benson, Arizona. 6 pages. November 28, 1966 (Volume 11)
  - Yuma -- Church of the Immaculate Conception
    - Baptismal Register. 1866-1880 (Volume 12)
    - Baptisms from La Paz, Ehrenberg, Prescott and Wickenberg. May 23, 1870-April 19, 1880 (Volume 12)
  - Solomonville
    - Baptismal Register. Includes in New Mexico (Buena Vista, El Paso, Lordsburgh and Virden) and in Arizona (Arivaipa, Bisbee, Bonita, Bowie, Camp Grant, Carlisle, Clifton, Dos Cabezas, Duncan, Fort Apache, Fort Thomas, Geronimo, Globe, Klondike, Lost Gulch, Metcalf, Morenci, Paredis, Pearce, Pima, Safford, San Antonio of the Gila, San Carlos, San Pedro, Stein Pass, Thatcher, Willcox, and Yachina). 1891-1905 (Volume 13)
  - Florence -- Church of the Assumption
    - Baptismal Register. 1870-1872 (Volume 14)
    - Confirmation Register. 1871-1881 (Volume 14)
    - Baptismal Register. 1883-1885 (Volume 15)
    - Confirmation Register. 1886-1896 (Volume 15)
    - Baptismal Register. 1886-1888 (Volume 16)
    - Baptismal Register. 1889-1900 (Volume 17)
    - Marriage Register. 1870-1880 (Volume 18)
    - Marriage Register. 1889-1954 (Volume 19)
    - Internment Register. 1871-1888 (Volume 20)
    - Internment Register. 1889-1957 (Volume 21)
  - Tombstone and Benson -- Church of Our Beloved Lady of Lourdes
    - Baptismal Register. 1881-1885 (Volume 22)
    - History of the Catholic Church in Benson & Tombstone. No Date (Volume 23)
    - Tombstone -- Marriage Register. 1881-1886 (Volume 23)
    - "History of the Catholic Church of Tombstone" by J.B. Salpointe, 3 pages. ca. 1881 (Volume 24)
  - Miscellaneous Lists
    - List of Parishes and Pastors in the State of Sonora Names of Priests Found in Baptismal Registers of theCathedral of Saint Augustine, Tucson Index to Baptismal Registers of Silverbell and Sasco, (The registers to which this index refers are not part of this collection but can be seen at the Diocese of Tucson Archives). 1903-1913 (Volume 25)